[Music]
purveyors of orthol like to talk about
how this lowc calorie sweetener is a
natural constituent of foods like melons
and peaches but it's in such tiny
amounts the average person only gets
like 25 milligrams and now that it's
manufactured commercially intake could
easily be a thousand times that I've
done a a few videos about it what's the
update well here's a paper with a Twist
arrol a non-nutritive sugar alcohol
sweetener and the main component of
Truvia brand sweetener is a palatable
ingested
insecticide huh yeah they found it
killed fruit flies and so they suggested
we start using rol as a safe sustainable
approach for Pest Control it evidently
induces in flies lethal regurgitation
also kills the yellow fever
mosquito
termites and ants so why isn't arol
sprayed on crops because it hurts the
crops too and the doses needed to kill
insects it has damaging effects on the
plant but hey if it hurts plants maybe
we can use it as an herbicide too okay
but what about just as a human sweetener
we've long known that the bacteria that
produce Dental plaque on teeth aren't
aren't fueled by orthol and they can't
seem to make acid out of it either to
cause cavities as long as plaque stays
above a pH of 5.7 food is safe for teeth
and swish with some ariol and nothing
happens whereas then swish with some
table sugar and pH dips down into the
danger
zone but Xylitol a sugar alcohol similar
to arol isn't just dentally safe in
terms of not causing cavities but may
actually have an active cavity stopping
benefit
seed Dental cavities are
reversible if detected and treated
sufficiently early early on we thought
that cavity reduction found in xotl
studies where people chewed on xotl gum
or sucked on xotl candies may have just
been due to indirect effects like
getting your saliva going or hey every
xotl candy maybe one less sugar candy so
maybe it's just a substitution effect
can you imagine how you might design a
study to test if there were Direct xot
effects I'll give you a moment to pause
try to come up with
something how about secretly randomizing
people to use xotl containing toothpaste
and indeed boom a reduction in tooth
decay compared to the controll
toothpaste without the xyl so xyl really
does seem to have cavity reducing
effects what about arrol then all
studies strongly support the idea of
arrol as being cavity reducing too
perhaps even more so than xotl for
example more than twice the drop in the
amount of plaque after 6 months sucking
on ariol candies versus xotl in fact
that extends out at least 3 years yeah
but did that actually translate into
fewer cavities we have all these studies
pointing in that direction however no
long-term human cavity trials on arrol
have been completed on until now a
doubleblind randomized control trial
involving hundreds of schools children
sucking on four arrol Xylitol or control
candies three times per school day and
arrol one the day significantly lower
number of cavity ridden teeth and
surfaces were found in the arrol group
another advantage to rol is safety to
dogs doses of Xylitol as little as a
half teaspoon in a 30b dog can be
lifethreatening whereas arral is so well
tolerated with no adverse effects
reported upwards of like more than a cup
a day suggesting it could even be used
as like an ingredient in chew toys or
something
[Music]